Good morning, so today's דף daf is ק"ה kuf-heh and we start
really with the very first line of ק"ה עמוד א', kuf-heh amud-aleph,
but I really wanted to spend just one second discussing some interesting
points about the issues that were raised yesterday, because we introduced this
issue about what's the final ברכה bracha of הבדלה havdala with this
question on עולא Ulla from a ברייתא braita about which types of
ברכות brachot that the general, the general structure that a ברכה bracha
normally if it's a short ברכה bracha is just ברוך אתה, Baruch
Atah, but if it's a longer ברכה, bracha, what I'll call a
paragraph ברכה, bracha, it starts with a ברוך אתה Baruch Atah and
ends with a ברוך אתה, Baruch Atah, but then there are exceptions.
A ברכה הסמוכה לחברתה bracha shesmucha lachaverta is a clear exception, the
ברכה bracha of קריאת שמע, Kriat Shema, exactly what the logic of
that is, maybe that's a type of a ברכה הסמוכה לחברתה. bracha
hasmucha lachaverta. Anyway, there are exceptions to the rule. So this leads
תוספות Tosafot to an interesting question and why we have this huge,
these huge תוספות Tosafot on ק"ד עמוד ב' kuf-dalet amud-bet for some
cases that don't fit. And I'm not going to go through all
of the cases that don't fit and all of his answers, but
I did want to highlight one or two. So if you take
a look at the תוספות, Tosafot, the first one, כל ברכה הפותח
בברוך, Kol Bracha Hapoteach beBaruch, okay,
you see there the תוספות Tosafot says the following. ותימא, Ve'teima, ברכת
אלוקי נשמה, Brachat Elokai Neshama, לא הוי סמוכה לחברתה, lo havei smucha
lachaverta, because in מסכת ברכות, Masechet Berachot, כי מיתער אומר אלוקי נשמה.
ki mita'ar omer Elokai Neshama. The גמרא Gemara says that when you
woke up, you didn't say מודה אני, Modeh Ani, but you said
אלוקי נשמה. Elokai Neshama. So it's
not was not originally סמוכה לחברתה. smucha lachaverta. Now what we do
when we say אלוקי נשמה Elokai Neshama is we normally do, what
do we do normally? ברכות
התורה?
Birchat HaTorah?
No, but what do we do before it? ברכות התורה? Birchat HaTorah?
Well, in most סידורים siddurim they have, they have, right, they have
אשר יצר Asher Yatzar right before אלוקי נשמה, Elokai Neshama, so you
end with the ברכה bracha of אשר יצר Asher Yatzar and then
you read into אלוקי נשמה, Elokai Neshama, you sort of make it
סמוכה לחברתה. smucha lachaverta. But תוספות Tosafot says that's not the original
way it was established. So why, how did it start? Independent, how
did it start without a
ברוך אתה? Baruch Atah? Okay. And his answer is ויש לומר v'yesh
lomar going down a few lines, beginning of the line, ויש לומר
לפי שאינם ברכות אלא שבח ותפילה בעלמא. v'yesh lomar lefi she'einam brachot
ela shevach v'tefila b'alma. Okay, now I don't really know what type
of an answer that is. Okay, it's not really the ברכה, bracha,
אלוקי נשמה Elokai Neshama is just like a praise. The real ברכה
bracha just begins at the end. But you could say that about
any paragraph ברכה bracha that doesn't begin with a ברוך אתה. Baruch
Atah. You're just saying some words of praise and then you're only
getting to the ברכה bracha part.
The אלוקי נשמה Elokai Neshama is a פיוט piyyut before the blessing.
Right, that's what he's saying. But it's a little bit funny because
obviously the whole way it's structured with a very specific text. Anyway,
one of the reasons why I did want to point that out
in addition to the problem is to note two things. Number one,
how we try to solve it by structuring אשר יצר Asher Yatzar
before it. And I have to tell you that sometimes when I,
for example, said אשר יצר, Asher Yatzar, whatever, get up, go to
the bathroom, etc., and I didn't say אלוקי נשמה Elokai Neshama right
afterwards, what I try to do is I try to say like
my ברכה bracha on ציצית tzitzit and then say אלוקי נשמה, Elokai
Neshama, so it's structured סמוכה לחברתה. smucha lachaverta. But again, תוספות Tosafot
is okay, that's nice to try to do it, but in its
principle, somehow it's not סמוכה לחברתה. smucha lachaverta. Now, as you nevertheless,
you don't start. I raise that because it's an interesting to think
about the flip case. About what would be if something was maybe
originally סמוכה לחברתה smucha lachaverta but then you separated it off, would
that change its status? So that specifically comes up in the question
of שבע ברכות. Sheva Brachot. And if you look at the next
תוספות, Tosafot, okay, he asks this question, there's two interesting points I
want to point out in this next huge תוספות. Tosafot. חוץ מברכה
הסמוכה לחברתה, Chutz mi-bracha hasmucha lachaverta, so second תוספות, Tosafot, right, פירוש
לפי
שחתם בראשונה אין צריך לפתוח השנייה בברוך. peresh lefi shechatam barishona ein
tzarich liftoach hashniya b'varuch. Okay, now he has a question. וברכה של
אחר ההפטרה, U'v'racha shel achar ha-haftara, דצור כל העולמים d'tzur kol ha-olamim
עד שכל דבריו הם אמת וצדק, ad she-kol devarav hem emet v'tzedek,
etc., we have שכל דבריו הם אמת וצדק. she-kol devarav hem emet
v'tzedek. ויש הפסק במחזורים, V'yesh hefsek b'machzorim, listen to his question. His
question is not that it's clear it's a separate ברכה. bracha. But
if you see the way it's written in the מחזורים, machzorim, it
says שכל דבריו הם אמת וצדק. she-kol devarav hem emet v'tzedek. Now
people know נאמן אתה הוא ה' אלקינו, Ne'eman Atah Hu Hashem Elokeinu,
right, ונאמנים דבריך ודבר אחד, v'ne'emanim devarecha v'davar echad,
so in the way it's printed in Artscroll, it's all one big
ברכה. bracha. ברוך אתה ה' הקל הנאמן בכל דבריו. Baruch Atah Hashem
ha-Kel ha-Ne'eman b'chol devarav. So it's not a problem. It starts with
a ברוך Baruch and it ends with a ברוך. Baruch. But his
problem is that in the מחזורים, machzorim, there's like a paragraph ends
and then a new paragraph, and he says it looks like the
first ברכה bracha doesn't end with ברוך Baruch and the second one
doesn't start with ברוך. Baruch. By the way it's printed in the
מחזורים. machzorim. So it's very funny the way he's asking the question.
By the way it's printed in the מחזורים machzorim it looks like
it's a problem. So let's see what his answer is.
I
think handwritten.
I guess,
yeah, handwritten clearly, you're right. I said printed but you're right, I
mean it's obviously right, we're dealing still with manuscripts. Right, I'm sorry.
ויש הפסק במחזורים, V'yesh hefsek b'machzorim, ומתחיל נאמן אתה, u'matchil Ne'eman Atah,
it's like a new paragraph too. ואין שם ברכה לא בחתימת הראשונה
ולא בפתיחת השנייה. V'ein sham bracha lo b'chatimat harishona v'lo bifteechat hashniya.
So the obvious answer is that there shouldn't be a break. But
the question is about the way it's written in the
מחזור. machzor. ונראה דכולה ברכה אחת היא דכולה משתעי בנאמנות ובאמיתות המקום,
V'nireh d'kula bracha achata hi, d'kula mishtayei b'ne'emanut u'va'amittut ha-makom, right,
נאמן אתה, Ne'eman Atah, right, הקל הנאמן, ha-Kel ha-Ne'eman, it's all one.
And just, you know, now's an opportunity, maybe the the the שליח
ציבור shliach tzibur pauses and everybody says something responsive. So what I
find fascinating about this תוספות Tosfos is, number one, the question is
not from the נוסח הברכה nusach habrachah but from the way it's
written in the מחזורים, machzorim, and that break suggests, you know, does
that suggest that it's two separate ברכות? brachot? And then the the
answer also, that there was almost this white space for people to
insert their own thing, you know, it to to me that very
connects to this אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach of פיוטים piyutim and so on
of inserting, you know, that was also, I mean obviously that wasn't
each individual did their thing, but a certain amount of flexibility, you
know, that that they would insert certain פיוטים piyutim into the standard
נוסח התפילה, nusach hatfillah, but as particularly around the ימים טובים. Yamim
Tovim. Maybe in some way this is a little bit more like
the ספרדי Sefardi practice of having a responsive component of the ציבור
tzibbur and having a type of a pause. I don't know the
specifics about what he was imagining or what he saw happen, but
anyway, that was an interesting phenomenon in itself. And now I want
to talk talk one other minute about his discussion of שבע ברכות,
sheva brachot, because in שבע ברכות, sheva brachot, the first three start
with ברוך אתה: baruch atah: ברוך אתה השם
שהכל ברא לכבודו—well,
Baruch atah Hashem shehakol bara
lichvodo thank you,
okay—שהכל ברא לכבודו, shehakol bara lichvodo, יוצר האדם, yotzer haadam, and אשר
יצר. asher yatzar. So why do those three also start with ברוך?
baruch? Now, the first two are easy, and if you skip later
in the תוספות, Tosfos, he says רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. I don't
know if you see it's like twenty lines down, the words line
starts with the word רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. ו-ר-ת vov-reish-tav with a
tship tship there. People see that? About twenty lines down the wide
lines, רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. Yeah, okay. רבנו תם אומר Rabbeinu Tam
omer דשהכל ברא לכבודו ויוצר האדם deshehakol bara lichvodo viyotzer haadam לכך
פותח בברוך lekach poteach bivbaruch ולא חתימה. velo chatimah. It's just a
simple—it doesn't end with a
ברוך—שהן קצרות כמו ברכת הפירות ומצוות, right? The short one-liners are just
ברוך, baruch ופתיחת זו היא חתימתן. upitichat hazu hi chatimatan. So there's
no idea of a חתימה, chatimah, the—you know, by the time you
get to the end, the end and the beginning it's all the
same. Okay, ואשר יצר את האדם—why vaasher yatzar et haadam does אשר
יצר asher yatzar start with a ברוך אתה? baruch atah? We said
יוצר האדם, yotzer haadam, we should have just jumped into, right, אשר
יצר את האדם בצלמו? asher yatzar et haadam btzalmo? We need another
ברוך אתה. baruch atah. So he says, ובאשר יצר את האדם צריך
לפתוח בברוך שאם לא היה פותח היה נראה הכל ברכה אחת. uvaasher
yatzar et haadam tzarich liftioach bivbaruch sheim lo hayah poteach hayah nireh
hakol brachah achat. He has a fascinating explanation. It's סמוך לחברתה, samuch
lachaverto, yes, but because the themes are so similar and maybe also
because the one that preceded it is a one-liner,
if you didn't start יוצר האדם yotzer haadam with ברוך אתה, baruch
atah, it would have seemed to be one big paragraph ברכה brachah
with—you know, I mean, if you didn't start אשר יצר asher yatzar
with a ברוך אתה, baruch atah, it would have been seen as
one big paragraph ברכה brachah with יוצר האדם. yotzer haadam.
So you could have solved this by the problem you had up
above: let them write it with a space in the מחזורים. machzorim.
No, but but that—yeah,
that would have solved it. But anyway, his—but I think it's fascinating
that he says, right, it's true, once you have this structure, if
you have סמוך לחברתה samuch lachaverto with a one-liner, not סמוך לחברתה
samuch lachaverto with a paragraph, but the one-liner preceded it, then then
by not having opening the next one with ברוך אתה, baruch atah,
you would have seen all of that as one and not as
two separate, particularly with with
יוצר האדם yotzer haadam and אשר יצר. asher yatzar. So anyway, just
to give you a sense of the types of issues תוספות Tosfos
is dealing with, and I did want to mention an important question
about this, because the big question comes up: are you allowed to
distribute the שבע ברכות, sheva brachot, which is clearly what we do
under the חופה? chuppah? But a number of פוסקים poskim say no,
because a number of them don't start with—after the—after the אשר יצר,
asher yatzar, they don't start with ברוך אתה, baruch atah, right? The
ones that follow, except the last one, because they're סמוך לחברתה. samuch
lachaverto. So he says, well, if you give them to different people,
they're no longer סמוך לחברתה. samuch lachaverto. Why? Because you're not saying
it סמוך samuch to your ברוך אתה. baruch atah. So רב משה
פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein says, not true, doesn't mean that you have
to say the ברוך אתה baruch atah that preceded it in order
to start the next one without a ברוך אתה. baruch atah. It
was—it was established as סמוך לחברתה samuch lachaverto
and therefore you—it doesn't have to be פותח בברוך. poteach bivbaruch. And
an interesting question would be, there's other הלכה halachah is is that
if you do the שבע ברכות sheva brachot out of order, it
still counts. So let's say you did it out of order and
you didn't—nobody, you know, nobody preceded it with a ברוך אתה—okay, baruch
atah but רב משה Rav Moshe still seems to say that it's
all about the way it was originally established and doesn't matter in
the execution exactly how that takes place. The last one starts with
a ברוך אתה, baruch atah, אשר ברא ששון ושמחה, asher bara sasson
vsimchah, because that one can exist independently. If you do, for example,
have שבע ברכות sheva brachot without פנים חדשות, panim chadashot, you would
do that one, you would do that one by itself, so that
one starts with a ברוך אתה. baruch atah. Yes,
Michael.
What constitutes a ברכה? brachah? Do you have to have שם ומלכות?
shem umalchut? Yes. Because so then so then that may answer why,
because in ברוך אלוקינו שבראנו לכבודו, Baruch Elokeinu shebaranu lichvodo, we don't
have שם ומלכות, shem umalchut, it doesn't start with ברוך. baruch, Right,
right. So that's not considered a ברכה? Bracha?
Exactly, exactly. Okay, so now, so that was all I wanted to
give you a sense of some of the fascinating discussions around this
whole structure of ברכות, Brachot, but now to actually begin the דף,
Daf, the top of ק"א ע"א, Kuf Alef Amud Alef, קשיא לאולא.
Kashya l'Ulla. So all of this is difficult to אולא. Ulla. Why
is this difficult to אולא? Ulla? Because אולא, Ulla, if you remember,
the whole story with sending אביי Abaye or actually רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda sending רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak to check up on what אולא
Ulla did, רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak sent אביי, Abaye, and it said
that all אולא Ulla did was he ended with המבדיל בין קודש
לחול. Hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol. Now, what was the problem? So the
רשב"ם Rashbam says the problem was was he just said a one-liner,
he said like the הבדלה Havdalah of רבי. Rebbi. תוספות Tosafot says
no then the, you know, and תוספות Tosafot the גמרא Gemara then
says it's קשיא לאולא Kashya l'Ulla because, you know, you're supposed to
be חותם בברוך. chosem b'Baruch. But then the תוספות Tosafot says that
can't be, then the answer is obvious, it's a one-liner, it's a
one-liner, there's no question here. So תוספות Tosafot says no, what happened
was was that אולא Ulla said all the things המבדיל בין קודש
לחול, בין אור לחושך, בין ישראל לעמים, Hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol, bein
or l'choshech, bein Yisrael l'amim, but he didn't have a חתימה, chatimah,
he didn't end it with anything. Now, it's hard to read that
exactly into the words of how it was described of what he
did, but that's what תוספות Tosafot says.
He didn't think he said
ברוך המבדיל בין קודש לחול? Baruch Hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol? Yeah, the
גמרא Gemara says he just said ברוך המבדיל. Baruch Hamavdil. So the
way תוספות Tosafot reads that is he just said the opening ברכה
bracha without the end. That's the way תוספות Tosafot reads that. Okay,
so this is the question. How did אולא Ulla do that? Let's
read it תוספות'ס Tosafot's way, it's a little more interesting. How did
he just do the opening ברכה bracha without the חתימה? chatimah? So
קשיא לאולא, Kashya l'Ulla, this is a difficulty to אולא. Ulla. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר לך אולא, Amar lach Ulla, אולא Ulla
will say to you, הני נמי כברכת המצות דמיין, Hani nami k'birchat
hamitzvot damyan, that's like a ברכת המצות, Birchat Hamitzvot, that's like a
one-liner. Why is it like a one-liner?
ברכת המצות מאי טעמא, Birchat hamitzvot mai ta'ama, why is ברכת המצות
Birchat Hamitzvot doesn't have to have an ending? משום דהודאה היא, Mishum
d'hoda'ah hi, it's a simple הודאה hoda'ah meaning it's not lengthy, it's
all one idea. You could also say like again there's no opening
and closing, the whole thing is a ברכה, bracha, is one ברכה.
bracha. הכא נמי הודאה היא, Hacha nami hoda'ah hi, here too it's
all one הודאה. hoda'ah. What does that mean? So what תוספות Tosafot
says it means, and this ties into the תוספות Tosafot we read
at the end of yesterday with why הטוב והמטיב HaTov vehaMetiv doesn't
end with a ברוך, baruch. that to say call it a short
or a long ברכה bracha is not just a question of the
length, it's a question of whether it introduces new themes. So that
the same way he said that, you know, the short ברכות brachot
because they're only one theme you don't end with a ברכה. bracha.
If you say המבדיל בין קודש לחול, בין אור לחושך, בין ישראל
לעמים, בין יום השביעי לששת ימי המעשה, Hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol, bein
or l'choshech, bein Yisrael l'amim, bein yom hashvi'i l'sheshet yemei hama'aseh, it's
all about המבדיל, המבדיל, המבדיל Hamavdil, Hamavdil, Hamavdil
and therefore does not require חתימה chatimah although it is lengthy in
actual length. And that's what תוספות Tosafot said the previous דף daf
about why for example הטוב והמטיב. HaTov vehaMetiv. So that's an interesting
idea that although for us the very fact that it's long sort
of, you know, almost asks for there to be some closure. According
to the way תוספות Tosafot reads this answer of אולא, Ulla, it's
that actually if it's just one theme, even if it's long, it
does not require a closing ברכה. bracha.
Like the blessing at the end of the מגילה? Megillah?
Yes, actually though that's an issue that תוספות Tosafot raised also and
he has his own discussion about that. Okay, obviously we don't do
that, we do have a חתימה. chatimah.
So it could be that we don't agree to that principle or
we think that it is considered to be different themes. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara continues. רב חנניה בר שלמיא ותלמידי דרב הוו יתבי
בסעודתא. Rav Chananya bar Shelamya v'talmidei d'Rav havah yasvi b'seudata. So רב
חנניה בר שלמיא Rav Chananya bar Shelamya and the students of רב
Rav
were sitting in a meal.
וקאי עלייהו רב המנונא סבא, V'ka'ei aleihu Rav Hamnuna Saba, and רב
המנונא Rav Hamnuna the elder was attending to them. Again, one of
these issues with people at the meal and somebody attending to them.
אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, זיל חזי אם איקדש
יומא, Zil chazi im ikadesh yoma, would you can you go check
if the day has become sanctified. So now we go back, remember
the discussion about פורס מפה ומקדש. poreis mapa u'mekadesh. Okay, so go
see if the day has become sanctified, if it's gotten dark, because
they were eating Friday afternoon. ונפסיק ונקבעיה לשבתא, V'nifsik v'nikbeiyeh l'shabata,
and then we'll interrupt and establish the שבת. Shabbat. Now, what does
it mean establish the שבת? Shabbat? Not clear, but by context in
the later description it sounds like they were saying we'll stop our
meal, we'll bench, we'll do like a סילוק השולחן, siluk hashulchan, maybe
we'll do like a type of a רב יהודה Rav Yehuda approach
and begin a new meal for שבת. Shabbat. אמר להו, Amar lehu,
so the attendant who they were sending on this little mission, so
now he's going to talk, he's going to tell them הלכה. halacha.
He says, אמר להו, Amar lehu, לא צריכיתו, Lo tzarichitu, you don't
have to stop your meal and establish שבת Shabbat with a new
beginning. שבתא קבעה נפשה, Shabata kava nafshah, שבת Shabbat establishes itself. Now,
what does that mean שבת Shabbat establishes itself? If you took that
literally you would say you don't even have to do פורס מפה
ומקדש. poreis mapa u'mekadesh. This could be like a רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yossi. The meal automatically becomes defined as a סעודת שבת seudat Shabbat
without you doing anything. Okay, from the later גמרא Gemara it's well
the next line we're about to read, it's going to sound not
that way. It's going to sound like because it enough defines itself,
it's sufficient to do פורס מפה ומקדש. poreis mapa u'mekadesh. You don't
have to start a whole new meal, but again not that you
don't have to do anything, although the simple read of the גמרא
Gemara would have suggested that. Let's continue to read and you'll see
why the ראשונים Rishonim don't say that. Okay, שבת Shabbat establishes itself.
דאמר רב, D'amar Rav, because רב Rav said, כשם ששבת קובעת למעשר
כך שבת קובעת לקידוש. Keshem sheShabbat kova'at l'ma'aser kach Shabbat kova'at l'kiddush.
The same way
שבת Shabbat establishes for מעשר. ma'aser. שבת Shabbos establishes for מעשר. Ma'aser.
It means that there's a הלכה Halacha that as long as
the grain that you have now harvested is not נגמר מלאכתו, nigmar
melachto, its processing has not finished, which means it's been threshed and
winnowed and made into a mound, and then actually even after גמר
מלאכה gmar melacha it has to be brought into the house. As
long as that has not happened, even before you've taken תרומות ומעשרות,
trumos u'ma'asros, you are, you can still eat from it אכילת עראי,
achilas aray, like not a set-down sit-down meal, but a little snack.
You're allowed to snack from it. So the גמרא Gemara says that
once it's שבת, Shabbos, it's no longer considered snacking. Once it's שבת,
Shabbos, שבת Shabbos is קובעת למעשר kova'as le'ma'aser because of the importance
of eating on שבת, Shabbos, the sense of, you know, enjoying yourselves.
So any eating you do on שבת Shabbos is not defined as
snacking. It's defined as really sitting down, having a סעודה, seuda, enjoying
yourself. Okay, that's the idea by מעשר. Ma'aser. So what's the, what's
the parallel? The parallel is that here too, by the קידוש, kiddush,
שבת Shabbos defines the nature of the meal. So the same way
there שבת Shabbos transforms
snacking and redefines it because it's שבת Shabbos as a סעודת שבת.
seudas shabbos. Here too, even if you were eating on Friday and
you would say, "Oh, it's a Friday meal, it's not a שבת
Shabbos meal, we have to redefine." No, שבת Shabbos comes along and
takes the meal and gives it a new identity and defines it
as סעודת שבת. seudas shabbos. תוספות Tosafos makes the parallel even stronger.
תוספות Tosafos says the הלכה halacha is, if you were snacking on
some grain out in the field on Friday afternoon and it became
שבת, Shabbos, then the same grain you were snacking on now you
can't, you have to stop snacking on it even if you were
in the middle of a meal. So he tries to make it
very parallel, that even in the middle of a meal, the presence
of שבת Shabbos redefines the nature of the eating that you are
doing. And therefore you do not have to actually stop the meal,
but again, you could have said you don't have to do anything,
but as we'll see, it's assumed to be, it's enough to be
פורס מפה ומקדש. pores mapa u'mekadesh. Okay. כשם ששבת קובעת כך שבת
קובעת לקידוש. K'shem she'shabbos kova'as kach shabbos kova'as le'kiddush. And that's actually
suggested in this phrase here. It doesn't say שבת קובעת עצמה. Shabbos
kova'as atzma. קובעת לקידוש, Kova'as le'kiddush,
establishes itself as a meeting of שבת Shabbos to require קידוש, kiddush,
right? So that still, yes, it's a סעודת שבת seudas shabbos now,
what do you do with a סעודת שבת? seudas shabbos? You have
to make קידוש. kiddush. So there's a need to make קידוש kiddush
now, but there's not a need to stop the meal and to
redefine it, to bench and to begin a new meal. Okay, so
סבר מינה, savar minah,
just have to, yes, that's the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains that.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So the גמרא
Gemara says, where were we?
Okay, so it says קובעת לקידוש. kova'as le'kiddush. So סבר מינה, savar
minah, we now, and now you'll see why the issue really is
that it's clear that you have to make קידוש. kiddush. סבר מינה,
savar minah, כהיכי דקבעה לקידוש, ki-heichi de-kav'ah le-kiddush, the same way it
establishes its identity, it's a סעודת שבת seudas shabbos and now you
have to make קידוש, kiddush, כך קבעה להבדלה. kach kav'ah le-havdala.
Similarly, in the, at the going out end. So there you are,
you're eating your שלוש סעודות, shalosh seudos, and it's now מוצאי שבת.
motzei shabbos. So if the presence of שבת Shabbos redefines the nature
of eating, of the meal, then the absence of שבת Shabbos redefines
the nature of the meal. So here I was, I was eating
שלוש סעודות, shalosh seudos, but it grew dark, all of a sudden
it stops being שלוש סעודות, shalosh seudos, now it's just weekday eating.
Well, weekday eating, what do you have to do before you do
weekday eating? You have to make הבדלה. havdala. So maybe the same
way, maybe I would be required to make הבדלה havdala now, the
same way I'm required to make קידוש. kiddush. So כך קבעה להבדלה.
kach kav'ah le-havdala.
So אמר להו רב עמרם, amar lehu Rav Amram, so רב עמרם
Rav Amram said, הכי אמר רב, hachi amar Rav, this is what
רב Rav says, לקידוש קובעת ולא להבדלה
קובעת. le'kiddush kova'as ve'lo le'havdala kova'as. Only for קידוש, kiddush, not for
הבדלה. havdala. And that's the way we rule, right?
Because otherwise you could not have your שלוש סעודות shalosh seudos all
the way out past dark.
I know, the ישיבה yeshiva would really have a problem. So anyway,
but this is how your סעודה שלישית seuda shlishis can go into
בין השמשות bein hashma'shos and into being dark without having to make
הבדלה, havdala, but if you're eating on Friday, you do have to
stop to make קידוש. kiddush. Now I do want to point out
something, although in the גמרא Gemara this is contrasting with the idea
of נפסיק nafsik if you were the position of רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, it's also rejecting the position of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi says if you're eating on Friday and it runs
into שבת, Shabbos, it's a continuation of the weekday meal, you don't
have to worry about it. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, when
it becomes שבת, Shabbos, it's now a שבת Shabbos meal, and a
שבת Shabbos meal demands קידוש. kiddush. But on going out, even though
it becomes a weekday meal in the, even though it became weekday,
it's not considered to do the same effect, and it doesn't make
it a weekday meal that now needs הבדלה. havdala. Okay, it's still
a continuation of the שבת Shabbos meal. So the question is what's
the difference? Why does it establish, change its identity going in, but
doesn't change its identity? Okay, so that's, so very good, you intuited
what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, but this is the
question, why is it not parallel? So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says
והני מילי לענין מיפסק דלא מפסקינן. ve'hani mili le'inyan mifsek de'lo mafsekinan.
And now that idea
that
שבת Shabbos establishes... Don't think that it means that you can start
eating on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* without making קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush*, right? I
mean so this is sort of like again we filled in some
of these blanks. Yes, you don't have to interrupt, but it doesn't
mean that you can just like... I'm sorry or no, I'm sorry
this is going, going out, excuse me. The fact, I'm sorry, I
said it wrong. So that's you don't have to interrupt your שלוש
סעודות *Shalosh Shudos*. הני מילי לענין מיפסק דלא מפסקינן *hani mili le-inyan
mifsak de-lo mifsakinan*, you don't have to interrupt your שלוש סעודות *Shalosh
Shudos* to make הבדלה Havdalah *Havdalah*. אבל אתחולי לא מתחלינן *aval atchulei
lo matchalinan*, you can't begin eating like after nightfall Saturday night and
this is the הלכה halacha *halacha* that you are not allowed to
eat without הבדלה Havdalah. *Havdalah*. Well that after שקיעה shkia *shkiah* also
not because of a ספק *safek*. This is actually important הלכה halacha
*halacha* that people aren't always so מקפיד *makpid* on this. The same
way you can't eat on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* when it gets dark
before making קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush*, you can't eat on מוצאי שבת Motzei
Shabbos, *Motzei Shabbos* before making הבדלה Havdalah. *Havdalah*. Presumably the reason is
the same, רב *Rav* Soloveitchik has a whole piece that he discusses
this, but presumably it's to give, you know, status and identity to
סעודת שבת Shabbos *Seudat Shabbat* by defining it by קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush*,
so then you also have to, not so much that you have
to define your weekday eating as סעודת חול *Seudat Chol*, then you'd
have to make it every single meal you had during the week,
but you define it by סעודת חול *Seudat Chol* by demarcating it
at the end point, you know at the boundary line from your
שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* eating. So the הבדלה Havdalah. *Havdalah* sort of demarcates
and now says the eating we're going to do from this point
on is going to be a different type of eating and that
distinguishes... it's very interesting, the whole focus on the eating as the
identity tied up with the nature of the day etc. So yes,
so it says you don't have to... so when you're going out
from שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* you don't have to stop to make הבדלה
Havdalah. *Havdalah*, but don't get, don't be, get me wrong. You still,
if you were to start eating then, you'd have to make הבדלה
Havdalah. *Havdalah* before you could eat. אפילו אכילת עראי *afillu achilas arai*?
Even אפילו אכילת עראי *afillu achilas arai* but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
going to suggest, even אכילת עראי *achilas arai* and so on. So
let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. אבל אתחולי לא
מתחלינן *aval atchulei lo matchalinan*, you don't start eating after it gets
dark before making הבדלה Havdalah *Havdalah*. ומפסקי נמי לא אמרינן אלא באכילה
*u-mifsak nami lo amrinan ella be-achilah*, and when is it that we
say you don't have to interrupt if you're having a שלוש סעודות
*Shalosh Shudos*, if you're doing eating. אבל בשתיה לא *aval be-shtiyah lo*,
if you're just drinking something on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* afternoon and it
gets dark, you have to interrupt because that's not a continuation of
a meal and therefore each like drink is really considered somewhat independent,
whereas a meal is defined by where it begins and that will
continue to be defined as סעודת שבת Shabbos *Seudat Shabbat*. ובשתיה נמי
לא אמרינן אלא בחמרא ושכרא *u-ve-shtiyah nami lo amrinan ella be-chamra ve-shichra*.
But the problem of drinking, right, is... oh
I think I explained it again wrong, I went back to the
שלוש סעודות *Shalosh Shudos*, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, let's do that again.
It's the same point but anyway, I'm sorry I did it wrong
again. Let's do it again. No, no I did it right, it
was ומפסקי נמי *u-mifsak nami*, it did say ומפסקי נמי *u-mifsak nami*.
Okay. אבל בשתיה לא ובשתיה נמי לא אמרינן אלא בחמרא ושכרא *aval
be-shtiyah lo u-ve-shtiyah nami lo amrinan ella be-chamra ve-shichra*. אבל מיא לית
לן בה *aval maya leis lan bah*. Right. So if you start
eating you don't have to, you don't have to interrupt for what
you eat. You do have to interrupt for your drinking, but if
all you're doing is drinking water, that's not a problem, because water
you can drink even after it becomes night and even after it
becomes the weekday. So what have we said? You don't start eating
once it's, once it's dark or maybe even בין השמשות bein hashmashos?
*bein ha-shmashos*, you don't start eating because you have to make הבדלה
Havdalah. *Havdalah* before you could eat. However, you can drink water. If
you started eating, however, before you can continue, you can continue eating,
but not if you've started drinking, okay. Precisely.
So drinking is only שכרא *shichra*? What about like other things in
between water, like milk?
Presumably not. Okay.
Presumably not meaning presumably
both, a, it doesn't count as having started on ערב שבת Erev
Shabbos *erev Shabbos* and you would have to interrupt, okay, and
and number two is that it, um, is that you wouldn't be
allowed to drink it, right. The only thing that is different here,
the only thing that you're allowed to continue is eating and the
only thing you're allowed to drink once it gets dark, and the
only thing you're allowed to do once it gets dark is drink
water. Okay, that seems to be the... and that, I'm sorry, that's
on the way out, and on the way out. No, no, on
the way in, I can't... even the way in, presumably not even
water. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. ופליגא
דרב הונא *u-fliga de-Rav Huna*. This argues on רב הונא *Rav Huna*.
דרב הונא חזייה לההוא גברא דשתה מיא קודם הבדלה Havdalah? *de-Rav Huna
chazaya le-hahu gavra de-shasay maya kodem Havdalah*. רב הונא *Rav Huna* saw
somebody drinking water before הבדלה Havdalah. *Havdalah*. אמר ליה Amar Lei, לא
מסתפי מר מאסכרה *amar leh lo mistafi mar me-askara*, are you not
concerned about אסכרה *askara*, which is basically what's, was like a respiratory
disease? I don't know how they translate it in English, anybody have
any translation? Croup is it? I think sometimes it's translated. A very
painful death. And this is because this idea that anybody that eats
or drinks anything once it becomes time for nightfall, once it becomes
you know מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbos *Motzei Shabbos* without making הבדלה Havdalah
*Havdalah*, is going to die in this painful death. Okay, so I
don't know exactly what the assumption of that link was, obviously somebody
putting something in your mouth and in your food and eating and
so on and this is respiratory, it talks about throat. דתני משמיה
דרבי עקיבא כל הטועם כלום קודם שיבדיל מיתתו באסכרה *de-tani mishme de-Rebbi
Akiva kol ha-to'em klum kodem she-yavdil misaso be-askara*. Okay, so I don't
know what to do about that strong statement, but anyway, here you
have that issue about whether you can begin eating,
drinking. When it becomes שבת, Shabbos שבת קובעת עצמה Shabbos kovaat atzma
which means you don't have to do בענטשן benching but you also
can't keep on eating. It demands that קידוש Kiddush be made, פריסת
מפה ומקדש. poris mappa umkadesh. Going out, we don't say the same
thing, that it demands that הבדלה Havdala be made. You can continue
eating if you started a meal, not drinking, but if you started
a meal. If you haven't started a meal going out, you can't
do anything except drink water, and even drinking water is debated.
A meal being המוציא, Hamotzi, right?
Presumably being המוציא, Hamotzi, right. דבי רב אשי לא קפדי אמיא. Debei
Rav Ashi lo kapdei amaya. Now, the house of רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, they didn't care about drinking water on מוצאי שבת, motzei Shabbos
they didn't feel it was a big deal. So בעי מיניה רבינא
מרב נחמן בר יצחק. baei minei Ravina meRav Nachman bar Yitzchak. So
רבינא Ravina asked רב נחמן בר יצחק: Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak: מי
שלא קידש בערב שבת מהו שיקדש והולך כל היום כולו. Mi shelo
kiddesh beerev Shabbos mahu sheyekadesh veholech kol hayom kulo. Okay, so, you
know what? So before we go on, did I skip a line
earlier?
Okay, whatever, hold on.
Okay, fine. All right, so, okay, so before we go on I
wanted to point out to you a תוספות. Tosafot. So תוספות Tosafot
says like this. Yeah,
והני מילי. vehani mili. You see the תוספות Tosafot והני מילי. vehani
mili. והני מילי דאכלו ושתו מעיקרא. vehani mili deachlu veshatu meikara. When
can you continue eating when it gets dark? If you've already started
eating like a שלש סעודות Shalosh Seudos before it got dark. So
he says, משמע שהיו אוכלין בשבת סמוך לחשיכה. mashma shehayu ochlin beShabbos
samuch lechasheicha. Right? Sounds like they started eating right before it got
dark. They started שלש סעודות Shalosh Seudos after מנחה. Mincha. ותימא שלא
נהגו לאכול בין מנחה למעריב. veteima shelo nahagu leechol bein Mincha leMaariv.
Right? Our מנהג minhag is that you don't begin eating even after
מנחה. Mincha. So how is it that people in the גמרא Gemara
clearly, you know, when you make שלש סעודות, Shalosh Seudos, before מנחה
Mincha or between מנחה Mincha and מעריב? Maariv? תוספות Tosafot does like
the גמרא, Gemara you made it between מנחה Mincha and מעריב. Maariv.
But we don't do any eating after מנחה. Mincha. וגם רבינו תם
כעס על רבינו משולם שהנהיג לאכול בין מנחה למעריב. vegam Rabbeinu Tam
ka-as al Rabbeinu Meshullam she-hinhig leechol bein Mincha leMaariv. דאמרי במדרש השותה
מים בשבת בין השמשות גוזל את קרוביו המתים. deamri beMidrash hashoteh mayim
beShabbos bein hashmashos gozel et krovav hametim.
Okay.
And then it comes after now. Why? וכך שמע פעם אחת עיר
אחת שמה לוטייר. vekach shama paam achat ir achat shema Lutier. There
was a,
this happened, that they had a, that they, you know, in לוטייר
Lutier which is the place presumably they started שלש סעודות Shalosh Seudos
between מנחה Mincha and מעריב Maariv ובא לידי סכנה. uva lidei sakana.
Okay, and תוספות Tosafot somehow saw that that was all connected. So
now what, the reason I wanted to show you this is because,
you know,
is מנחה Mincha and מעריב Maariv the idea of בין השמשות? bein
hashmashos? If it is then it becomes a הלכה halakha. question. When
are you allowed to start? Does it have to be before שקיעה
shkia. or could it even be בין השמשות? And people know sometimes,
you know, so we've got to get a move on in מנחה
Mincha because people want to wash and people want to start the
meal, at least wash which officially starts the meal before שקיעה. shkia,
So that's like a הלכה question. When are you allowed to start?
Do you have to start worrying about it, you know, at שקיעה,
shkia? or can you even start after שקיעה? Shkia. This idea that
you can't eat before הבדלה. Havdala But this language of גוזל את
המתים, gozel et hametim, you know, גוזל את קרוביו. gozel et krovav.
And this suggests another issue which you might be aware of which
also comes up in the whole idea of drinking water. There's this
whole sort of like a mystical approach, right, that the dead get
a reprieve on שבת. Shabbos And שבת Shabbos the, you know, that's
their day off, and they're not burning in the fires of גיהנום.
Gehennom. Okay. When שבת Shabbos is over, they all have to go
back to גיהנום. Gehennom. And שבת Shabbos being over is not just
that three stars came out, but that you as the ציבור tzibur
have finished. They've done דאוונען, davening, they've made הבדלה. Havdala Okay. So
number one, that's a reason to postpone ending שבת Shabbos because you
give the dead some more time off, you know, their one day
off, their furlough day. But then the idea also becomes that if
you start like drinking the water and so on, drinking before, that's
sort of, you know, that's the water that they are going to
be using to cool off, and you're being גוזל gozel it from
the מתים metim in your eating and so on before הבדלה. Havdala,
Exactly exactly.
I don't know, I believe that that is, you know, definitely a
way in which that is understood. You understand? There they are, they've
got a day off from the rivers of fire, and they're in
some nice river of water which they're going to stay in until
you made הבדלה. Havdala And now you're drinking, you're like taking away
their
water before you make הבדלה.
Havdala I know. Well, I don't know if your eating is postponing.
The postponing is a different חשבון cheshbon from your eating. Well, all
right, anyway, anyway, so תוספות Tosafot doesn't spell it out, but I
definitely believe that that is, you know, a way in which this
whole thing is understood. I want to read you also a line
from the ראש. Rosh. I can't take up too much time, we
have to go on, but I want to read you a line
about this issue as well. He says like this. He goes,
this is in יג. yud-gimmel. He says, רבינו תם כעס על רבינו
משה Rabbeinu Tam ka-as al Rabbeinu Moshe he has not Rabbeinu Meshullam
שהנהיג לאכול she-hinhig leechol משום דאמרינן השותה מים בשבת בין השמשות גוזל
את המתים, mishum deamrinan hashoteh mayim beShabbos bein hashmashos gozel et hametim,
etc. וגם רב שלום
מצא בכתב, vegam Rav Shalom matza bichtav,
right? So this is a גאון. Gaon. שתיקנו לומר
צדוק הדין, shetiknu lomar Tziduk Hadin, right? Why say צדקתך? Tzidkatcha? על
שמת משה רבינו באותה שעה. al shemeit Moshe Rabbeinu beota sha-ah. וגם
נהגו vegam nahagu not to fall מדרש *midrash* between the תפילות *tefillos*,
don't tell anybody about the דף יומי *Daf Yomi*
and we also have these speeches, what constitutes מדרש *midrash*? משום דחכם
שמת בית מדרשו בטלים *mishum dechacham shemeis beis midrasho biteilim*. ומנהג אבותינו
תורה היא *uminhag avoseinu torah hee*, okay, etcetera, etcetera. So he's, and
the fact that it sounds that they ate late, that meant before
שקיעה *shkia*. Okay, but they didn't actually eat after שקיעה *shkia*. But
this becomes the interesting idea that you I'm sure have heard, משה
*Moshe* died on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, בין השמשות *bein hashmashos* sort of
at the leaving of שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, etcetera. And he surmises that
this is also the מנהג *minhag* of צידוק הדין *tziduk hadin*, the
מנהג *minhag* that they have not to have public learning, תשכחא *tishkachah*,
and somehow presumably connected to this idea of you don't want to
start eating during this time period. But again, you could have made
it a completely הלכה *halachic* discussion. Since it's already post-שקיעה *shkia*, it's
in the potentially post-שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* period, so therefore it's הבדלה Havdala.
*havdalah* time, so therefore don't start eating. So it's funny how all
these other ideas get brought in. When is that moment that you
cannot begin eating, after שקיעה *shkia* or like after צאת *tzeis*? Okay,
and here the whole, but they're bringing in a lot of these
other issues to definitely be part of that discussion
and the פרקי אבות *Pirkei Avot* for instance, because, yeah.
You think
that they're using this as like a scare factor that they didn't
use the הלכה *halachic* reason like you said? They used the more
anecdotal?
Yeah, I don't know. It's funny why of all things did they
need this as a scare, I think they really had these concerns.
These seem like very real, and רבנו תם *Rabbenu Tam* said the
סכנה *sakana* happened because of that. I think these mystical things were
very alive for them. I don't know if they're just using it
as a way of getting people to comply, I don't think that
that's it.
Similar, it's a similar idea that קדיש *Kaddish*, that regarding קדיש *Kaddish*
has to do with the נשמות *nishamos* of the deceased.
Right, right, exactly.
One last point also to get back to Michael's point, if you
look at the רשב"ם *Rashbam* five lines from the bottom לא קפיא
מייא *lo kapya mayya*, he says קמי הבדלה Havdala *k'mi havdalah* אבל
מקמי קידושא *aval mik'mi kiddusha* five lines from the bottom of the
רשב"ם *Rashbam* middle of the line לא קפיא מייא *lo kapya mayya*,
קמי הבדלה Havdala, *k'mi havdalah* אבל קמי קידושא קפיא *aval k'mi kiddusha
kapya*, even those that didn't care about water before הבדלה Havdala. *havdalah*
would care about it before קידוש Kiddush *kiddush* משום כבוד kavod שבת
Shabbos *mishum kavod shabbos* והכי הלכתא *ve'hachi hilchasa*. Okay, and then he
goes on. So anyway, I just wanted to point out that this
discussion of water before הבדלה Havdala *havdalah*, which is the one thing
that might be okay, is at least according to the רשב"ם *Rashbam*
not, never debated regarding שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, regarding קידוש Kiddush *kiddush*.
Okay, so but I mean if they're really saying this is a
סכנה *sakana*, there shouldn't be חמירא סכנתא *chamira sakanta* from everything in
case you should.
Let's move on. Okay, so we have the idea don't eat before
הבדלה Havdala *havdalah*, maybe water and again I just got a little
the significance of that and distinguishing the סעודת שבת Shabbos *seudat Shabbat*,
but if you started a meal beforehand and a discussion what when
are you allowed to start before שקיעה *shkia* or after שקיעה *shkia*,
started a meal beforehand then you can continue. Let's take a look
now at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. It says like this, בעי מיני
רבינא מרב נחמן בר יצחק *ba'ei minei Ravina me'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*,
רבינא *Ravina* asked רב נחמן בר יצחק *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*. מי
שלא קידש בערב שבת Shabbos מהו שיקדש על כל היום כולו *mi
shelo kiddesh be'erev shabbos mahu she'yekadesh al kol hayom kulo*. You forgot
to be מקדש mekadesh *mekadesh* on ערב שבת Shabbos *erev shabbos*, can
you be מקדש mekadesh *mekadesh* the rest of the day? Now part
of this question is let's say you forgot to be מקדש *mekadesh*,
the way to read it is Friday night, can you say the
full קידוש Kiddush, *kiddush* שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* morning? That's obviously a reasonable
question. It is interesting to understand the phrase מי שלא קידש ערב
שבת Shabbos *mi shelo kiddesh erev shabbos* as opposed to לילי שבת
Shabbos, *leilei shabbos*. ערב שבת Shabbat *erev shabbos* is ערב שבת Shabbat.
*erev shabbos*. And the רמב"ם *Rambam*, we normally assume you're making קידוש
Kiddush, *kiddush* because שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* has already begun. But the רמב"ם
*Rambam* says that the idea of קידוש Kiddush *kiddush* and the idea
of הבדלה Havdala *havdalah* is to demarcate something at the beginning and
at the end and therefore he says the idea of קידוש Kiddush
*kiddush* is to make קידוש Kiddush *kiddush* at the beginning of שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos* or before or after a little bit. Demarcate something roughly
at the beginning. It doesn't have to be the second שבת Shabbos
*Shabbos* begins, it doesn't have to be after שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* begins,
but you want to demarcate it somewhere around the beginning time. So
according to the רמב"ם *Rambam* when you make קידוש Kiddush *kiddush*, no,
not before, well you could, but whatever, when you make קידוש Kiddush
*kiddush* you don't necessarily begin, it's not necessarily a קבלת שבת Shabbos.
*kabbalat shabbat*. It doesn't have to be a קבלת שבת Shabbos *kabbalat
shabbat*. You're allowed to make קידוש Kiddush *kiddush*, right,
on Friday afternoon. And similarly, yeah, because you're designating the day that's
come. Similarly, you're allowed to make הבדלה Havdala *havdalah* before שקיעה *shkia*.
You can make, don't light a candle, don't do the אש *esh*,
but you can make הבדלה Havdala *havdalah* and it accounts for הבדלה
Havdala *havdalah* if you do it anytime after פלג המנחה Plag HaMincha,
*plag hamincha*. That's actually the הלכה *halacha*. Now you're not supposed to
unless you're like דחוף לדבר מצווה *dachuf l'devar mitzvah* and so on,
but technically it counts. I'll tell you this comes up for me
because I wait רבנו תם *Rabbenu Tam*, I wait 72 minutes, but
I will be making הבדלה Havdala *havdalah* for my family, somebody else
lights the candle, I'll make הבדלה Havdala *havdalah* for my family before
the 72 minutes because you can make הבדלה Havdala *havdalah* early anytime
after פלג המנחה Plag HaMincha *plag hamincha* because the idea of demarcating
can be roughly around the beginning or the end even if it's
still Friday, even if on one end or even if it's still
שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* on the other end. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara's*
question could be, besides just can you make it שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*
morning, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara's* question could be let's say it's midnight
Friday night, it wasn't ערב שבת Shabbos. *erev shabbos*, it wasn't around
the beginning, right, can you then you still make קידוש. Kiddush Okay,
so I think the use of ערב שבת Shabbos is interesting. So
let's see what the answer
is. אמר ליה, he said back to
him, מדאמר ליה, MiDe'Amar Lei, since the children of רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiya say מי שלא הבדיל במוצאי שבת מבדיל והולך כל השבוע כולו,
MiSheLo Hivdil B'Motzei Shabbos Mavdil V'Holech Kol HaShavua Kulo, if you didn't
do הבדלה Havdala. on מוצאי שבת Shabbos you can do it for
the rest of the week, not literally the rest of the week,
but through Tuesday. הכי נמי, hach nami, so you see, okay, ideally
it's supposed to be at that point, you know, at that line,
but if you missed it, you can do it later. הכי נמי
מי שלא קידש בערב שבת מקדש והולך כל היום כולו, hach nami
mi shelo kidaysh b'erev shabbos mikadaysh v'holech kol hayom kulo, you can
do it the whole rest of the day, you can even do
it at סעודה שלישית Seuda Shlishis time if you forgot. It'd be
funny to do קידוש Kiddush and right afterwards הבדלה. havdalah Now that's
like a good, that would be a good quiz question. When can
you make קידוש Kiddush and two seconds later make הבדלה? havdalah. So
it's like two minutes before פלג המנחה, Plag HaMincha? you forgot to
make קידוש Kiddush the entire שבת, Shabbos so you make קידוש Kiddush,
now, then there'd be פלג המנחה Plag HaMincha and you'd make הבדלה.
havdalah I wonder if you can make קידוש Kiddush after פלג המנחה?
Plag HaMincha? פלג המנחה's so early you
can make הבדלה havdalah פלג המנחה?
Yeah, it's an hour or so before שקיעה. Yes. Oh what?
That's an easier answer to the
question. What? יום טוב? Yom Tov?
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, that's true, but on a plain שבת Shabbos
right, okay. Anyway, okay. איתיבי, Esvei, let's try
this. לילי שבת ולילי יום טוב, Leilei Shabbos V'Leilei Yom Tov, here's
a תוספתא, Tosefta, שבת Shabbos, nights and יום טוב Yom Tov night,
beginning of שבת and יום טוב, Yom Tov, יש בהן קידוש על
הכוס, yesh bahen kiddush al hakos, you do קידוש, Kiddush sanctification on
the כוס, kos, ויש בהן הזכרה בברכת המזון, v'yesh bahen hazkara b'virchas
hamazon, you mention then, you do רצה Retzei or יעלה ויבוא. Ya'aleh
V'Yavo. שבת ויום טוב, Shabbos V'Yom Tov, on the day of שבת
and יום טוב, Yom Tov, אין בהן קידוש על הכוס, ein bahen
kiddush al hakos, you don't make קידוש, Kiddush meaning you make בורא
פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen but you don't say a special ברכה
bracha of קדושה Kiddushah מקדש השבת Mekadesh HaShabbos or anything, ויש בהן
הזכרה בברכת המזון, v'yesh bahen hazkara b'virchas hamazon,
but you still do the regular mentioning of them in ברכת המזון.
Birchas HaMazon. ואי סלקא דעתך מי שלא קידש בערב שבת מקדש והולך
כל היום כולו, V'ei salkah daitach mi shelo kidaysh b'erev shabbos mikadaysh
v'holech kol hayom kulo, if it's possible to make שבת קידוש Kiddush
on שבת day if you forgot it on שבת night, שבת ויום
טוב נמי משכחת לה דיש בהן קידוש על הכוס. Shabbos V'Yom Tov
nami mishkachas lah d'yesh bahen kiddush al hakos. What do you mean
you don't have a קידוש kiddush, שבת day or יום טוב Yom
Tov day? It can happen. דאי לא קידש מאורתא מקדש למחר? D'ei
lo kidaysh me'ovya mikadaysh l'machar? If you forgot the night before, you
would make it on שבת day. So the גמרא Gemara gives the
obvious answer: אמר ליה דאי לא לא תני. Amar lei, d'ei lo
lo tana. What if we're not talking about? Okay, we're not talking
about crazy scenarios. As a rule, you make קידוש kiddush only on
שבת and יום טוב Yom Tov night and you don't make it
on שבת and יום טוב Yom Tov day. איתיבי, Esvei, okay, I'll
try again. כבוד יום וכבוד לילה. Kvod yom v'kvod layla. If you
have to make a decision, you have limited funds. Should you spend
more money on making a nice Friday night meal or a שבת
day meal? כבוד יום קודם. Kvod yom kodem. So the honor of
the day comes first actually, which is an interesting idea. Okay. Why
exactly this is, there's a lot of קבלה Kabbalistic reasons around these
issues, but let's just anyway read the הלכה. So if you have
to have limited funds, give more significance to the כבוד of the
day. ואם אין לו אלא כוס אחד, V'im ein lo ela kos
echad, but if you have only one כוס kos of wine and
you have to choose where to use that כוס kos of wine
for, אומר עליו קידוש היום מפני שקידוש היום קודם לכבוד יום.
omer alav kiddush hayom mipnei she'kiddush hayom
kodem l'kvod yom.
So you use that Friday night because it's more important to have
the קידוש היום, Kiddush HaYom, not meaning daytime, but the קידוש kiddush
of שבת which is the nighttime קידוש kiddush because we say מקדש
השבת, Mekadesh HaShabbos, rather,
what could you use the wine for? You could use the wine
for your meal during the day and that would give more honor
to the day meal. Everybody likes to drink during the meal. So
we have this one cup of wine, should we use it for
קידוש kiddush Friday night, or should we use it to have a
nicer meal שבת day? Everybody just
calm down, the גמרא's Gemara going to discuss it. So you say,
so the answer is although normally we give do nicer food for
the day if you have to make a choice, but if it's
between קידוש kiddush and a nicer meal, you're going to give preference,
privilege, to קידוש at night. Now the גמרא Gemara asks the question
which is why we quoted it, Michael, that Michael wants to ask,
ואי איתא, v'ei issa, if you could actually, it's possible to make
שבת קידוש in the daytime, to make the Friday night קידוש in
the day, דשבקיה עד למחר? dishbakhei ad l'machar? Don't use the cup
of wine on Friday night, leave it over to the meal to
שבת day, ולעבדי תרתי, v'leividi tarti, and get two for the price
of one. Make קידוש, make the Friday night קידוש in the day
and drink it during the day meal, which makes the day meal
a little bit nicer than the night meal. So the גמרא Gemara
says: אמר ליה חביבה מצוה בשעתה. Amar lei, chaviva mitzvah b'sha'atah. א
מצוה A mitzvah is dear in its right time. You know, yes,
you could do it late, but that's not the right time to
do it. There's a very special role that it plays when it
comes to particularly the קידוש idea, you know, more than other things,
you know, it plays a very important role when it comes at
the beginning. So בדיעבד bedieved can you still come later? Yes. But
that's not its right place. And therefore we're not going to postpone
it.
Well you still don't drink,
make קידוש on a פת? pat?
That's going to come up too.
Okay, could you also מקדש on the פת? pat? So yeah, so
that's an interesting question. Why didn't you, why weren't you just מקדש
on bread? So that also could indicate how strong the preference is
for wine over bread. But you are, you are correct, that that
could have been, you know, that that also is a question here.
Okay, why you didn't make קידוש with bread? Wait, so why why
don't you drink making קידוש *Kiddush*? All right, that's going to come
up too. Oh, but wait, okay, he also מקדש *Mekadesh* on the
פת *pas*, so... Yeah, so that's an interesting question. Why didn't why
weren't you just מקדש *Mekadesh* on bread? So that also could indicate
how strong the preference is for wine over bread. But you are
correct that that could have been, you know, that that also is
a question here. Okay, why you didn't make קידוש *Kiddush* without drinking
from it we'll discuss. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this:
ומי אמרינן חביבה מצוה בשעתה chaviva mitzvah besha'ata. *Umi Amrinan Chaviva Mitzva
Besha'ata*, do we really say that the מצוה *Mitzva* is dear in
its right time and that that's such an important principle that makes
us give up this thing, give up nice having wine during the
meal, והתניא *ve-hatanya*, we taught a ברייתא braisa *Braisa*: הניכנס לביתו במוצאי
שבת *ha-nichnas le-veiso be-motzaei Shabbat*, we quoted this before. You come home,
it's Saturday night from שול shul *shul* presumably, מברך על היין ועל
המאור ועל הבשמים *mevarech al ha-yayin ve-al ha-maor ve-al ha-besamim*. You do
הבדלה havdalah, *Havdalah*, יין מאור ובשמים *yayin maor u-vesamim*. This is the
שיטה *shitta* of בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* that מאור *maor* comes before
בשמים *besamim*. ואחר כך אומר הבדלה havdalah, על הכוס al hakos. *ve-achar
kach omer Havdalah al ha-kos*. ואם אין לו אלא כוס kos אחד
*ve-im ein lo ela kos echad*, if you only have one cup
of wine, מניחו עד אחר המזון *menicho ad achar hamazon*. You wait
till after you're done eating. So this sounds like it's a different
scenario, you were eating and it became מוצאי שבת *Motzaei Shabbat*, but
it could mean the way תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* understands it is you
know you're going to have a meal and you're going to want
that כוס kos *kos* of wine to בנץ *bench* on that cup
of wine. So what you do is, the way תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot*
understands this, we'll actually let you have your meal before you've made
הבדלה havdalah *Havdalah* in order that you can use that one cup
of wine to do double duty, for ברכת המזון birkat hamazon. *Birkat
Hamazon* and for הבדלה havdalah. *Havdalah*. So what do you do? מניחו
עד אחר המזון *menicho ad achar hamazon*. Oh, by the way, I
should have mentioned although you say הבדלה *Havdalah* in שול shul *shul*,
right, you say, you know, in the שמונה עשרה *Shmoneh Esrei* and
the גמרא *Gemara* is going to reference that in a minute, that
doesn't allow you to eat. It has to be the same way
the קידוש *Kiddush* that you say in שול shul. *shul* when שבת
*Shabbat* begins, you know, that you say in the דאווענען *davening* it
does not allow you to eat. The קידוש *Kiddush* that's מתיר אכילה
*matir achila* on Friday night and the הבדלה *Havdalah* that's מתיר אכילה
*matir achila* on Saturday night is when it's connected to the meal,
is when it's done on the כוס kos. *kos* of wine. Okay,
so here you are, you came home, right, you all know this,
right? Just because you דאווענען *davened* in שול shul *shul* doesn't mean
you can eat before making קידוש *Kiddush*. The same is true about
הבדלה *Havdalah*. Okay, so here it is, you came home. According to
תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* we're going to let you eat because you only
have one cup of wine and מניחו עד אחר המזון *menicho ad
achar hamazon*. You wait, use that cup of wine after בנצ'ינג *benching*
ומשלשלן כולן לאחריו *u-meshalshelan kullan le-acharav* and you בנץ *bench* and then
you have the הבדלה *Havdalah*, you string it on, you know, you
chain it afterward. Okay, so now the question is why do we
let you postpone הבדלה *Havdalah*, eat, בנץ *bench*, do all these things?
Why don't we say, "Excuse me, time for הבדלה *Havdalah*, make הבדלה
*Havdalah* on the כוס יין kos yayin, *kos yayin* and you won't
have a כוס יין kos yayin. *kos yayin* for בנצ'ינג *benching*. גאר
נישט געפערלעך *gar nisht geferlech*, whatever, tough luck. Do the מצוה *mitzvah*
at the right time. Don't manipulate things in order to get two
for the price of one." So you see we do manipulate. What's
the choreography?
You say ברכת המזון birkat hamazon *Birkat Hamazon*, then you say בורא
פרי הגפן
borei pri hagafen *Borei Pri HaGafen*,
then you go right into הבדלה *Havdalah*.
And the בורא borei פרי הגפן *Borei Pri HaGafen* counts both ways.
Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says, "Look at the introductory paragraph, yes
you could say it I assume, but yes, even without that." ולא
אמרינן חביבה מצוה בשעתה chaviva mitzvah besha'ata *ve-lo amrinan chaviva mitzvah be-sha'atah*.
We don't say just make הבדלה *Havdalah*, don't worry about ברכת המזון
birkat hamazon. *Birkat Hamazon*, do it at the right time. So you
see there we do manipulate. So if we manipulate, why didn't we
say if you have only one cup of wine, wait till the
morning and use it for both? Okay, so must be, says the
גמרא *Gemara*, you can't do קידוש *Kiddush* in the morning. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said back to
him, "Look, אנא לא חכימא אנא *ana lo chakima ana*, I'm not
so smart, ולא חוזא אנא *ve-lo chuza ana*, I'm not a seer,
I'm not like a prophet, ולא יחידא אנא *ve-lo yachida ana*, and
I'm not also, like, you know, making this up by myself. He
says, I don't know any חכמות *chakmos*, you're too smart for me.
But אלא גמירנא וסדירנא אנא *ela gmirna ve-sadirna ana*, I'll tell you
what. I've learned this tradition, I've organized the material. I don't know
that I have answers to your questions, but I'm not making this
up. This is my tradition. וכן מורין בבי מדרשא כוותי *ve-chein morin
be-vei midrasha ke-vasi*. And by the way, it's not, you know, this
is the accepted הלכה *halacha*. You go to the בית מדרש *beis
midrash*, you ask around, this is how everybody understands it. If you
missed it Friday night, you can make it שבת *Shabbat* day. You
have a question? Good question. I don't know the answer, but let
me tell you, this is the הלכה *halacha*." Okay, this is, I
think it was רב נחמן
בר יצחק *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak* was responding to רבינא *Ravina*. Okay,
by the way, interesting different language of גמירנא וסדירנא *gmirna ve-sadirna*. We
mentioned before סודר מעשה בראשית *suder ma'aseh bereishit*. So the רשב"ם *Rashbam*
says, right, so that one is to actually get the information and
the other is to organize the information. But he's saying, but I'm
still not making it up myself, this is clearly the tradition. Okay,
so שאני לן בין עיולי יומא לאפוקי יומא *shani lan bein ayulei
yoma le-afukei yoma*. Now here's the answer. Now by the way, here
is the answer, it's interesting whether the גמרא *Gemara* is now saying
the answer or he's saying the answer after saying you're too smart
for me, I don't know. But anyway, here's the answer. שאני לן
בין עיולי יומא לאפוקי יומא *shani lan bein ayulei yoma le-afukei yoma*.
There's a difference between starting the day and ending the day. Okay,
and this goes also to the point that Michael made before. עיולי
יומא *ayulei yoma*, starting the day, כל כמה דמקדמינן ליה עדיף ומחבבינן
ליה *kol kamma de-maksheminan leh adif u-mechabevinan leh*. The sooner you could
start it the better and we show it's dearness to us. So
therefore we don't say wait, hold up the כוס יין kos yayin
*kos yayin*, let's make קידוש *Kiddush*. שבת day. Don't use it Friday
night. No, שבת is starting. You want to show how much you
love שבת, you want to make קידוש, you want to use that
כוס kos of wine, that's חביבה מצוה בשעתה. You're going to want
to make קידוש Friday night. You don't want to show that you're
postponing your affirmation of it being שבת or your designating of it
being שבת. So that's why we do that then. So but
אפוקי יומא, apukei yoma, but the going out, הבדלה case you asked,
you said, oh just make הבדלה right away, why do we wait
and manipulate it with the בענטשן? benching? There's a reason, because מאחרינן
ליה, machrinan leh, we try to postpone making הבדלה at the end,
כי היכי דלא להוי עלן טעונא, ki heichi delo lehavei alan tituna,
it shouldn't be like a burden. And this becomes as we know
a general principle of besides תוספת שבת tosefet Shabbos at the out
at the going out, that you don't end שבת immediately, but I
mentioned this before like when it's חנוכה, Hanukkah, you first light the
חנוכה ליכט Hanukkah licht and then you make הבדלה, we do things
to show that we're not eager to that you know to make
for שבת to end. So he says, look, there, there's not big
pressure make הבדלה as soon as possible. Actually the pressure is the
opposite, post try to postpone הבדלה a little bit. So we'll first
בענטש bench and then make הבדלה. Have a nice long סעודה, seuda,
but Friday night have a nice long סעודה, seuda, but Friday night
there it's going to be different and Friday night if you have
a כוס kos יין, you use that for קידוש even though בדיעבד
bediavad I'm still saying that if you didn't make קידוש you could
make it שבת day. So the position is בדיעבד bediavad you could
make it שבת day, but you certainly do not try to make
that happen, you try to your you know do it obviously Friday
night חביבה מצוה בשעתה to show that you are starting שבת. Yes.
So again just if you if you made הבדלה
as a plug as a plug on שבת day, so what's a
נפקא מינא nafkmina in terms of איסורי מלאכה issurei melacha for example?
Like why would you what difference would it make?
No no no the day is still halachically שבת. There's absolutely no
question, yeah, I mean I hope that was not unclear. No I
don't care if you're יוצא yotzei הבדלה, it's still שבת, it's still
שבת. Right. No the significance is you were יוצא yotzei your חיוב
chiyuv of הבדלה. That's it. I'll give you a small context every
night I told you is I come home and it's over שבת
for my family but not for me and I can make הבדלה
for them. But another scenario is I'm here at the I have
to I have to catch a cab the minute שבת is over,
okay, and I'm going to have to be totally ready to go
dot dot dot dot dot I'll make הבדלה before and the cab
is going to show up at my house literally the minute שבת
is over. I'm going to make הבדלה before שבת is over and
then run out and catch a cab.
So forget the
הכנה hachana question.
No you have everything ready from before שבת, you have your suitcase
ready, whatever.
Fine.
Where's that נר ner from?
So you don't do it on the נר. ner.
Okay. What what a play ball out.
Right right right I said you don't go ahead and light a
candle you don't light a candle obviously, you don't do מלאכה. melacha.
What? No. And then when you see a נר ner מוצאי שבת
you'll do it. When you get to the airport you'll grab you
know you'll take two matches and you'll do a בורא and you'll
do a בורא מאורי האש. borei meorei haesh. Behind security guards.
Exactly. You go to the smoking section of the bar or something.
Okay anyway. So let's take a look now the גמרא says now
we're going to get into very interesting halachic discussions about הבדלה so
about from this teaching about coming home from שול shul and only
having one כוס kos and having to manipulate it in order to
do הבדלה and ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon So the גמרא says שמע
מינה shema mina we can infer so now we're done with this
discussion that בדיעבד bediavad yes you can make קידוש during the day
but we certainly try to make it as much you know all
effort at night. Now שמע מינה shema mina we can infer from
this whole thing about coming home from שול and making הבדלה
where am
I מהמתניתא mehamasnisa תמני tamni eight. So I'm always saying the גמרא
says שמע מינה shema mina תרתי tarti but here there are really
a lot of things to learn from this ברייתא braisa. and there
are eight even though eight is not at all a magic number
there are here's the things to learn from this ברייתא. braisa שמע
מינה המבדיל בתפילה צריך שיבדיל על הכוס, shema mina hamavdil betefila tzarich
lehavdil al hakos, presumably you're coming home from where? You're coming home
from שול. So presumably even though you're coming home from שול you
have to make and you said הבדלה in שול right because you
say it in שמנה עשרה, shemoneh esrei, you have to say it
again על הכוס.
al hakos, From the ברייתא braisa right above.
From the ברייתא right above, coming home and making הבדלה and then
waiting for ברכת המזון birkat hamazon and so on. ושמע מינה ברכה
טעונה כוס veshema mina bracha teuna kos we also see that you
have to now ברכה bracha here means ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon Okay
because obviously the whole discussion about הבדלה has been about has been
about you know כוס kos יין. But you see that you have
to make ברכת המזון על הכוס, birkat hamazon al hakos, right? Because
if you didn't have to make ברכת המזון birkat hamazon על הכוס
al hakos what are we manipulating and first you have your ברכת
המזון birkat hamazon dot dot dot all of that is an assumption
that ברכת המזון birkat hamazon. has been has to be על הכוס.
al hakos. Okay that's number two.
Where am I
okay. ושמע מינה veshema mina and we also hear from this כוס
של ברכה צריך שיעור kos shebracha tzarich shiur that there's a minimum
size of the כוס. kos Why? Because if there's no minimum size
I got a great solution. What? I don't have enough wine? I'll
pour tiny little you know like the little one ounce thimbles and
I'll have a כוס kos, for ברכת המזון birkat hamazon, and a
כוס for הבדלה. Okay, so clearly I can't do that. Clearly there
is a minimum
amount. Okay, ושמע מינה המברך צריך שיטעום. ushma mina hamivarech tzarich sheyitom.
There's your answer Michael, that when you do the ברכה bracha you
have to taste it. Because if you didn't have to taste it
there's another solution: make the ברכה bracha and make the הבדלה and
then don't drink the wine and then use the same כוס for
ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon So you see you have to drink. Now
תוספות Tosafos, says maybe not you, somebody has to drink, it doesn't
personally have to be you necessarily, although it's interesting, it's a ברכת
הנהנין, birchat hanehen, the whole issue about the בורא פרי הגפן becoming
a ברכת הנהנין birchat hanehen but then getting its identity also as
part of the ritual of the of the קידוש of the הבדלה.
But anyways someone has to drink because if nobody had to drink
from it there would be no need to to do to have
to do double duty.
I would have expected a לשון lashon here of רוב כוס rov
kos or something.
Well that's an interesting question but it might not be. But it
might not be רוב כוס. rov kos. Okay but you drink a
little then you don't have... ושמע מינה ushma mina we also hear
from here טעמו פגמו, ta'amo pagmo, as soon as you taste it
you have been פוגם, pogem, you have, you know, what's the word
for פוגם? pogem?
Stigmatized it or whatever you've sullied it or you know it's actually
also has the sense of like you've been מחסר michaser it, like
you know you've taken something away from it. But anyway you can't
use that wine anymore. How do I know that? Because if you
could you have a solution. Let's assume we said fine that there
is a minimum amount but presumably it doesn't mean you have precisely
a רביעית, revi'is, maybe you have a רביעית revi'is and a half.
The גמרא said presumably we're having that's a possible scenario. So why
don't you just drink the half of the רביעית revi'is for הבדלה
and use the rest of the רביעית revi'is for ברכת המזון, birkat
hamazon right? Why can't you do that? Take a little sip and
use the rest, you know if you have a little bit more
than a than a רביעית revi'is you have a solution. It must
be that no, that once you've taken a little bit of a
sip you have actually made the wine unusable. What about adding more
in? ושמע מינה ushma mina what more?
You only have your רביעית revi'is and a half, pour your רביעית,
revi'is, you know you still have a little half an ounce there,
drink a little bit.
No, the whole wine that's left in the כוס is no longer
usable.
No, but then pour some from a bottle back in.
So we don't know that that works, okay? That might not work.
I mean that's what we do but that might not work. The
wine is considered unusable at this stage. ושמע
מינה טעם מבדיל. ushma mina ta'am mavdil. What you also hear is
that we let this guy eat in order to get the כוס
to use for ברכת המזון birkat hamazon and הבדלה and now he's
making הבדלה, that even once he has eaten, even if בדיעבד b'di'avad
you ate, you're not supposed to eat before הבדלה, but if you
have eaten before הבדלה you can still do הבדלה. Okay, so we'll
end with that, we'll do the rest of the ושמע מינה's ushma
mina tomorrow, but I want to just end by saying one important
thing because it's just come up. The assumption, one of the ושמע
מינה's ushma mina is you do ברכת המזון על הכוס, al hakos
right? The assumption. Now if you look at תוספות, Tosafos I mean
we don't tend to do that, if you look at תוספות, Tosafos
ושמע מינה ברכה טעונה כוס, ushma mina bracha teuna kos, the third
ושמע ushma in תוספות, קצת משמע דאפילו ביחיד טעונה כוס, kzat mashma
de'afilu beyachid teuna kos, even if there's only one guy doing ברכת
המזון you have to do it on a כוס,
דהנכנס משמע שהוא יחידי. dehanichnas mashma shehu yachidi. Okay and then he
goes on and on and at most he says alright maybe you
don't need it unless there are three. But it sounds like even
one, maybe only three, but you know then he acknowledges, תוספות says
that we certainly don't do it על הכוס al hakos? if we're
doing it individually. Okay but the reality is that the פשט pshat
of the גמרא is you always need a כוס יין for ברכת
המזון and תוספות was at most willing to say maybe when you
have three people.
Have you seen a ראשון rishon for that yet?
Why you need it על הכוס? al hakos, Same idea that you
need it for these other things: אין אומרים שירה אלא על היין,
ein omrim shira ela al hayayin, you know? But actually
I quoted you that that wasn't in the גמרא yet, okay? So
I don't know, you have to take a look at the discussion
about how this practice developed, especially if you think about in the
time of the ראשונים Rishonim they certainly had plenty of wine going
around there, you know that was their business, but it is interesting
that the simple sense of the גמרא is you always have to
do it על הכוס, ושמע מינה ברכה טעונה כוס, ushma mina bracha
teuna kos, and we barely do it except maybe sometimes only when
we have a מנין. minyan. Okay, to be continued tomorrow.